<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A prayer, or, Petition for peace November 22, 1645.</title>
            <author>Eleanor, Lady, d. 1652.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1647</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 5 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 6 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A36417</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing D2003</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R37762</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">17014079</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 17014079</idno>
            <idno type="VID">105779</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A36417)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 105779)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1614:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A prayer, or, Petition for peace November 22, 1645.</title>
                  <author>Eleanor, Lady, d. 1652.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>8 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] printed :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1645 [i.e. 1647]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title (p. 3): A prayer and petition for peace / by the Lady Eleanor.</note>
                  <note>Imprint suggested by Wing.</note>
                  <note>2 blank leaves, with ms. bibliographic notes, bound in front of t.p.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Prayers for peace.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:105779:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 109 -->
            <p>A PRAYER, OR Petition for <hi>PEACE.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>November 22. 1645.</p>
            <q>
               <p>Behold, your houſe is left unto you deſolate. And Verely yee ſhall not ſee mee tell yee ſay bleſſed is hee that commeth in the name of the Lord.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Printed in the Yeare 1645<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:105779:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 110 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:105779:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 110 -->
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:105779:3"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 111 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:105779:3"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 111 -->
            <head>A PRAYER AND PETITION for Peace.</head>
            <byline>By the Lady <hi>Eleanor.</hi>
            </byline>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Lord, the great and dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full God: As we having ſinned deeply and offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded guilty of no leſſe then <hi>open Rebellion: by our excluding thee, flee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from thy preſence,</hi> with one voice (as it were) <hi>We will not have this man to raigne over us</hi> (or) <hi>He defers his coming,</hi> as others: Even departed from Thy precepts and Iudgements ſet before us, ſo here proſtrate before the foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoole of thy Throne, implore never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the<gap reason="illegible: damage" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſe
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:105779:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 112 -->pardon and forgiveneſſe.</p>
            <p>For this no ſtolne or ſecret tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gresſion committed, <hi>But with a high hand, and ſo much the rather preſuming on ſuch acceſſe, becauſe the vulgar, (the bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then and heate of the day though theirs,) thoſe ſheep not guilty or acceſsary to this treſpaſſe or Capitall crime: of depoſing thee,</hi> or oppoſing the LORDS Returne as in not harkning to the loud voices of the Prophets accompli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, His Meſſengers. But to our Kings, Princes, Heads and Rulers, which appertaines, ſo ſtraitly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded and charged in readyneſſe to be and watch, and ſignes of the time, they diſcerning them not, <hi>ſuch</hi> celeſtiall ſignes and tokens, wherefore haſt watcht over them, as ſince this a Nation, or under the whole Heaven
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:105779:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 112 -->the like unknowne of thoſe Vials <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> violently powerd out (without doubt) <hi>Not ſince the Flood as in this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Century.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Neither taking warning by our neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours houſes ſet on fire firſt, like his ſeting in the front the handmaids and their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, or like that great Maſſy Jmage,</hi> firſt ſmitten in the feet, by that ſtone without hands cut out, before broken in peices, And thus before hand thought others as lighted Becons for <hi>our uſe yet like the reſt lightly weighed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Till ſuddainly like Sampſons ſeven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold new cords and green Wyths all pluckt aſſunder; when linked ſo faſt and knit, France</hi> with great <hi>Britaine, Spaine</hi> with <hi>France, Germany</hi> with <hi>Spaine,</hi> Toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with theſe married Iſles or united Kingdomes, now in widdowes wofull
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:105779:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 113 -->eſtate, or as <hi>the</hi> divorced: ſomtime th<gap reason="illegible: damage" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> as it been a new world, with ſuch <hi>crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> flouriſhing, and new <hi>names,</hi> and ſo walking like dayes of old,, when he voted out was to the open fields, No leſſe then is not this great <hi>Babylon,</hi> and become as thoſe, when God repented he made <hi>man,</hi> brought to a like Ebb or fall, as thoſe inſaciable Giants.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Now behold O Lord through a high and heavie hand abaſed and ſo low brought humbled to aſhes and Sackcloth from the higheſt to the lowest, then tread not one a Worme, breake not the bruiſed reed, the wounded ſmite them not,</hi> but heare us O thou our Anchor, hope and preſent helpe, ready to be conſumed utterly and ſwallowed up, if thou calme not and aſwage theſe tempeſtious working Seas through unruly raging winds let
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:105779:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 113 -->looſe, wrought and contrived, and ſo praying in His poſture when as with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <hi>raine</hi> ſo long 42. moneths, even bowing himſelfe double or kneeling on his head, alſo behold our eſtate ſince the yeare 1642. theſe miſerable Iſles <hi>and Kingdomes of ours whoſe ſtore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſes exhauſted like thoſe rivers dried up and like the dead trees burnt up our nation and habitation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To conclude; <hi>Bleſt as thoſe</hi> two and forty unhappy INFANTS torn by two <hi>ſhe-Beares,</hi> and as Gods curſe upon them, ſo Lord let thy face ſhine upon us, cauſe thy voice to be heard, that ſome time ſpeakeſt to the <hi>Fiſh,</hi> the <hi>fig-tree,</hi> the deafe, the dead, and very Divels ſubject, and turneſt the hard Rocke into ſtanding waters, &amp;c.
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:105779:6"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 114 -->alſo the waters of this <hi>CJTJE</hi> heare them, for the Lords ſake our only Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, ſay the word and <hi>it is done,</hi> that from hence forth, let there be no more <hi>Death,</hi> &amp;c. no more Killing and Slaying, <hi>J</hi> beſeech thee.</p>
            <trailer>FJNIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:105779:6"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 114 -->
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
